Do folks know what this is?
There's [INAUDIBLE] Stanford.
That's Stanford [INAUDIBLE].
You know which one?
Old person.
What is this?
What's going on here?
The first Dartmouth [INAUDIBLE].
That's right.
And then--
What is the association
to Stanford here?
I believe this is [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
He started Sail, if I
understand correctly.
Is that right?
He started Sail?
Yeah, I think he did.
But anyways.
So what's interesting is--
So it's amusing to actually look
at what they wrote in there.
I don't know if it was
a brochure, or what.
But they wrote in
there their goals.
The font is a bit small.
So the study is to proceed on
the basis of the conjecture
that every aspect of
learning or any other feature
of intelligence can, in
principle, be so precisely
described that a machine
can be made to simulate it.
Fantastic.
So single machine.
You want to simulate all
of human intelligence.
And a carefully selected
group of scientists--
and we think that we
can make, actually,
the paragraph right before the
second set of red underlines,
is--
we think that a
significant advance
can be made in one or
two of these problems
if a carefully selected
group of scientists
work together for a summer.
I don't think they knew of
AI winters then, actually.
They didn't know of it then.
And the third thing I'm using
is-- but the major obstacle
is not lack of machine
capacity, but our inability
to write programs taking full
advantage of what we have.
So while the goals
were noble, it's
surprising how wrong
you can be in--
with some of the smartest
people in the room.
So Selfridge, a
neural network OG
that wrote the
original pandemoniums--
I think he got
everything, basically,
except problems with
black box optimization.
Then Minsky.
Of course, Shannon.
Solomonoff-- I think
this is Solomonoff MDL.
In many ways, you can argue
that's the underpinning
of self-supervised
learning today.
But it's really amazing
to see the first--
at least I don't
know if we'll be
able to characterize
or write down
all the rules for intelligence.
So you can imagine
the approaches
they were taking were all
these rule-based systems.
And they couldn't be more
wrong on machine capacity.
Today's transformers are-- they
don't-- they're data centers.
And I guess they needed a
really, really long summer
to solve this one.
But yeah.
So it's 1955, so
about, yeah, 60 years--
no, no.
Getting close to 70 years.
And we're basically talking
about the same problems
again, except maybe
some things work.
Some things don't work.
And this talk is
about some of the--
one of the pieces that has made
this larger enterprise work.
And we're getting closer to the
original goals of the Dartmouth
Conference.
Yeah.
Again, so this is the big gaps.
So what eventually happened
in the field was that
their goal of having a single
system that explained most of--
that was able to mimic our
cognitive abilities, which
would definitely mean
image processing,
or image understanding
and language processing
as well, that--
the field got-- a single
model or a single approach
to do all these things
was shattered by thousands
of different research projects.
So there was no consolidation.
But here's another.
This is going to
be a harder one.
Can you tell what
is a-- this is 2009.
And this a-- this is
not a single system.
This is a complicated
machine translation system.
So when I started my PhD,
machine translation systems
used to be a bit more
complicated than this, actually.
Thousands of pipeline systems.
You had to first
extract-- you had
to first do word alignments that
actually looked like attention.
It's like [INAUDIBLE] attention.
Then, based on that, you
extracted how larger phrases
aligned with other phrases.
Then you had to figure out
how to-- how they-- then you
had to teach.
There was some machine
learning there.
You had to teach your
model how to score them
connecting with each other.
So can you-- does
anybody know where
a neural network is in this?
All right.
So this is a machine
translation system from 2009.
And CSLM is a Continuous
State Language Model
that they would
use for re-scoring.
So the world was
so discrete then
that you had to call these
models Continuous State Language
Models.
And it was largely inspired
by the Neural Probabilistic
Language Model by--
oh, it doesn't appear.
Huh.
Sorry.
Oh, there, the Neural
Probabilistic Language Model
by Bengio, I think
it was, in 2003.
And so we were--
even in 2013, when I published a
paper on neural network language
models, these models were still
being put into the feed forward.
Neural network language
models were still re-scoring.
And now, it's incredible
if you think about it, just
in terms of consolidation, how
all of these complicated systems
that have now been
replaced by just
neurons that talk to each other.
And you just learn
the rules from-- you
just learn the rules
from data automatically.
So it's fun to--
it's interesting to see.
And since then-- so this is
what the NLP 2013 conference
was like.
You see these different--
these-- you can
call it verticalized
NLPs, different areas
like morphology, dialogue,
and discourse.
I don't even know if people
talk about [INAUDIBLE]
this talk tomorrow.
I don't know if there's
a research track anymore.
Then there is a
machine translation.
So there's opinion mining
and sentiment analysis.
Now models make
you angry or upset.
And so you could see
that, just in 2013,
the field-- even research was
divided into these smaller
tracks.
And everybody had
their own specific--
they were bringing their own
specific domain information.
And they had to specialize
in a domain in order
to solve some task.
And we solved tasks
to some degree.
Machine translation-- probably
because of a lot of government
funding as well, we have
made a lot of progress.
And we were making practical
translation systems that were
being deployed in the wild.
Google Translate was a
great example of that.
And so since then, you
have this-- we started to--
first, we all agreed we
need distributed word
representations.
And you saw this.
People probably
remember this funky
embedding algebra, King minus
Man plus Woman equals Queen,
from Word2Vec.
And we had a--
there was a big industry
of models that actually--
that just-- that learned
word representations.
And these word
representations were actually
useful in downstream tasks.
And then came another step
in this process, where now we
started saying, OK,
these representations--
they're only helpful if
they're learned in context.
So the King should change based
on context, the King of Persia,
or the king has no clothes,
or the emperor has no clothes.
And so we saw these--
we saw approaches
like sequence-to-sequence
to sequence learning,
where we started to formulate.
We started to create these
general formulations of how
to solve any task in NLP.
So sequence-to-sequence
formulation--
you can formulate
many tasks in language
as sequence-to-sequence,
question answering,
machine translation, dialogue.
And then, of course, we had--
then we developed
attention, which
was a very effective,
content-based way
to summarize information.
Typically, you have these
encoder-decoder architectures.
Everybody is probably,
I'm guessing,
familiar with encoder-decoder
architectures, right?
So encoder-decoder architecture,
in a position on the decoder
side, could summarize,
based on its content,
all the information on
the source sentence.
And this is a really
effective, content-based way
of summarizing information.
And what started
happening was we started--
these general paradigms
started coming up.
Sequence-to-sequence
learning can solve--
it can install most
language problems
because most language
problems have
to deal with learning
representations
of variables length.
The goal is to learn
representations
of variable-length sequences.
And if you do that successfully,
you can then potentially
solve that problem.
And then attention
was an excellent way--
a content-based way to
actually summarize information
from some neighborhood.
And the major
workhorse until then
were these recurrent
models, or LSTMs,
where, basically, the method
was typically the same.
You had a sentence, and
you crushed the sentence
into a set of vectors that are
representations, one typically--
typically, one
for each position.
And the way LSTMs
did it was where
they walked along the sentence.
They ate up a
word, and then they
summarized the entire history
into one fixed bottleneck.
And that bottleneck
was then transmitted--
was updated based
on the next word.
And if you were successfully
able to learn representations,
then we could solve these tasks
like translation summarization
dialogue.
So an important movement.
And in 2020, I--
I guess, when was the
sequence-to-sequence learning
papers?
2015 NeurIPS.
Then we saw the attention
paper in-- around 2015, 2016.
And the machine
translation community
was the first to
respond and say,
hey, machine translation is a
classic sequence-to-sequence
learning problem.
Why don't we now first
start re-scoring?
And then can we
still build native
to really rethink
machine translation
with these
sequence-to-sequence models?
And these are fantastic models.
I don't know if you guys have
ever done these exercises on--
LSTMs can count.
For example, if you train
an encoder-decoder on--
to model a to the n, b to
the n-- so you feed in n a's.
And you ask the decoder
to predict n b's.
And you-- actually just
a single-cell LSTM--
if you know the
structure of an LSTM,
there's a cell that
basically keeps--
so it's a notion of state.
And just a single cell
is able to actually
just do trivial counting.
It counts how many
a's you consumed,
and then it decrements it.
And then when you
consume all the-- exactly
the same number of b's as
the number of a's, something
lights up and says, I'm done.
I've recognized this language.
So you can train trivial
like a to the n, b to the n.
And here, you have a--
I'm sorry this is not clear.
But you have somewhat of a--
you have a grammar here.
And you can see that
these are different cells.
This is about eight cells here.
And each one of
these cells actually
increments its counter once
it reads a particular symbol.
And it's able to actually
track how deep you
are in this hierarchy
and this grammar.
And Google, of course--
the crowning
achievement, perhaps,
of sequence-to-sequence models,
which I was actually right--
I was fortunate to be
in the same cubicle
as it was being-- as
this work was being done,
was the Google Neural
Machine Translation System,
where they took LSTMs.
They added many
advancements towards a lot
of systems, improvements to a
lot of data that Google had.
And they produced
what you might--
at that time, the
state of the art
neural machine
translation system
and sequence-to-sequence models.
So now this big, consolidated--
this big, complicated system,
which looked much
more complicated,
had now become a homogeneous--
just a single homogeneous neural
network.
So at that time, the biggest
frustration we had was--
the LSTMs were the
primary workhorse.
And the biggest frustration
we had was, they--
Not only were we producing.
Not only were we--
did we produce
the output autoregressively.
We were sequentially decoding
the output left-to-right.
But also, we were reading
the input sequentially.
So you had to--
In order to produce the
representation for the 10th
word, you had to eat up the
first word, the second word,
the third word.
So that was really slow,
and not the whole--
and another big
problem with LSTMs
were that you have
this bottleneck
that basically-- that
contains all the information
about your past.
So you have to now crush--
you have to pack both
long-distance interactions
that you might have
and local interactions
through the single fixed vector
that you need to transmit.
And sequentiality doesn't--
inhibits parallelism,
which means that you
couldn't even read.
The encoder couldn't even
read the sentence in parallel.
And of course, decoding
was auto-regressive.
So you couldn't even
write in parallel.
And convolutions
were-- they were
starting to emerge as
a solution, largely.
They had been very successful
in computer vision.
They had also figured out
how to optimize them while--
how to make them--
how to train--
how to make them really
fast on GPUs, where--
because they're just basically
matrix multiplications.
And matrix multiplication
is largely--
it's parallelizable.
So convolutions were a
solution to this problem
of not being able to read in
parallel because you could-- in
parallel, every word,
basically, produced
its representations by
looking at its neighbors,
its local neighbors.
And there were some very--
there were some breakthrough
papers, such as ByteNet,
for machine translation,
the Convolutional Sequence 2
Sequence model that
was contemporaneous
to the transformer, actually
probably predated it
by a few months, where
they used convolutions
both in the encoder and decoder
to get good scores on machine
translation that were better
than the Google Neural Machine
Translation System.
And of course, probably
the most successful
was WaveNet, which was a
text-to-speech system that was
state of the art at the time.
So convolution still had
this problem that-- one,
I guess-- they were
parallelizable.
But the issue was that you
still-- you couldn't directly
capture long-distance
interactions between-- you
couldn't directly capture
long-distance interactions
between words.
So if you're basically
a receptive field--
if it's a 3 by 3--
If it's a 1 by 3, then it
basically grows linearly
with the factor of--
it grows linearly
with the number of layers
each time it expands by 3.
So you still needed a
linear number of layers
to capture these
long-distance relationships.
But attention, on
the other, hand
was this really effective
mechanism that we knew was--
that could actually get us--
In one, it could actually
capture all the interactions
between one word
and every other word
using content-based addressing.
Because convolutions
basically match--
convolutions match
weights with parameters.
Attention was actually able
to use content with content.
So based on how similar
I am to my neighborhood--
based on how similar
I am to my neighbors,
I'm going to absorb
that information.
And this actually-- this motif
actually appears everywhere,
even in computer vision.
So maybe, actually,
I can go there.
So here's a-- in vision,
there's this approach.
Do people here know
of non-local means?
So in computer vision, there's
an approach called non-local
means that's basically--
it was originally developed
for image denoising.
So if you want to
denoise an image patch,
you basically-- you look
at all your neighbors,
and you see which patch
is very similar to you.
And based on the
similarity, you actually
pull in that information.
And this largely works
in images because images
are very self-similar.
They start sounding like,
hey, based on content,
I want to pull in information.
And again, there were similar--
there were approaches like
Texture Synthesis
by Efros, where,
if you wanted to do painting,
or if you wanted to generate
an image, then you would look at
a patch that's similar to this
rectangle in some other--
in your dictionary,
or in a database that
you have of patches.
And then, based on what's
closest, you actually bring it.
So you bring that patch,
and then you Paste it there.
So these approaches
that look like attention
were already prevalent.
It's a very natural formulation.
And the ByteNow paper had shown
that this actually works really
well for language as well.
So the question then
was, why can't we
then learn representations?
Instead of doing this
source target, why can't we
actually learn representations
by the sentence attending
onto itself?
So now you basically use--
instead of attending-- a
source sentence attending
to a target sentence, can
it just attend to itself?
And the original goal of
actually when we wanted--
when we were-- when we wanted to
actually do parallel decoding--
So attention by
construction is paralyzable
because each token can basically
construct its representations
from its neighbors in parallel.
And it directly captures
token-to-token interactions
because now, of course, we'll
run into complexities of length.
But we can-- and
we'll discuss how
to solve some of these things
later, or overcome them.
But you can direct-- instead
of having this linear growth
and receptive field,
you can directly
capture these interactions
because convolutions-- if you
have a very, very
large receptive field,
it gets computationally
very expensive.
And it also had
these explicit gating
and multiplicative
interactions, which
we've often seen in Gated
PixelCNN, or [INAUDIBLE]..
These explicit gated
multiplicative interactions
have typically helped
training and have
led to better accuracies.
And as I mentioned, the original
motivation of why we actually
wanted to do this was-- we
said, hey, so the LSTMs are--
we have good
translation systems.
But the problem is that,
actually, both reading
and writing, sequentially-- can
we actually do both in parallel?
So we wanted to read the
German sentence in parallel
and then translate it, and then
also write in parallel by that.
Instead of actually decoding
it autoregressively, can you
decode it-- instead of
decoding it in time,
can you decode it in height?
So you first spit out one word.
Or you spit out all the words,
and you iteratively refine them.
And this was-- this turned out
to be very, very challenging
and hasn't been solved
successfully until today.
Because the biggest challenge,
essentially, is, when you--
whenever you're
decoding, essentially,
as you predict a word, you bend
the probability distribution
that then nails down--
narrows down what you're
going to predict later on.
And the ordering that
allows you to basically--
the ordering that allows
you to nail these modes
was very hard to learn.
So imposing left-right
ordering is much easier
than actually not
having one and having
to learn it as you're decoding.
So the original approach
just didn't work.
But then we still
had our salvation
in being able to
read parallelly.
So we said, all right,
let's take this back
to the encoder-decoder models.
And unlike-- at that time,
there were a few formulations.
So we had this--
the original formulation
of attention from Graves.
Then we had the Additive
attention formulation.
And we took the Dot-Product
attention formulation,
largely because it
allowed us to do--
because it allowed us
to actually do attention
as a matrix multiplication.
And oftentimes, some of
the biggest constraints
that actually-- physics
is such a big constraint
in neural networks
that, if you can
make your architecture amenable
to modern accelerators,
you have a much better
chance of succeeding.
And Dot-Product attention
could be expressed
as a matrix multiplication.
And there are already
kernels for being
able to do matrix multiplication
very effectively on the GPU.
So the formulation was--
all right, so now we have--
similar to the
Dot-Product attention,
we had a scaling
factor, simply because--
if the Dot-Product
actually becomes too big,
and you can solve it under
certain assumptions of mean
and variance in the
representations,
you can [INAUDIBLE].
Oh, it hasn't updated, actually.
Yeah.
So our formulation
is-- basically,
you have your queries,
which, what you end up
doing is-- if you
have a position,
you first project
it into queries.
And then the same token--
the representation
of the same token
gets projected into
also keys and values.
And the first-- the
query determines
how much you're actually going
to pull from all these keys.
So you first do a Dot-Product
of the query with every key.
And then, based on
that, you combine,
or you pool the content
of all these positions
based on what the score
was after normalizing
it using a softmax.
So in some sense, you can
think of self-attention also as
a content-based
pooling mechanism.
And the scaling factor
basically avoids you--
it saved us from these logits
actually blowing up in training,
becoming unstable.
And on the decoder side,
you could trivially--
you can trivially
implement causality by just
adding an attention mask.
And what this-- where this
brings us is that-- all right.
So now we've solved.
So a caveat on the FLOPs.
We'll actually cover this later.
But now what we have is a
mechanism that's parallelizable.
It gives you direct content.
It gives you direct
token interactions,
which we'll-- and that we
believe is going to help you
actually learn and model these
relationships between the words
better.
And the complexity
of self-attention
is faster than convolutions
because convolutions
are quadratic in the number.
They're quadratic in
the number of channels
and the number of-- in
the hidden dimension.
But self-attention is
quadratic in the length.
So if your length is not much
more than your hidden dimension,
you've actually saved on FLOPs.
Now, this is not quite
a complete picture
because not all FLOPs are equal.
And we'll talk
about this later on.
And now, when you put
everything together, what we--
basically, we took the basis.
This has a very
strong similarity
to the ResNet
architecture, actually.
So if you look at ResNets--
so in ResNets, you
have contraction.
You have spatial mixing
with convolutions.
And then you have
the expansion again.
The transformer--
if you just adjust--
if you just move
it one step down,
it's very-- it's analogous.
You have attention.
Then you have
expansion-contraction.
But there is a
difference in where
the residual connections are.
But it's a very similar
basic building block
with the residual connections.
And you have these
contractions and expansions.
And then the
transformer-- those were--
that was multi-head attention
with expansion-contraction,
which was in the
feed forward layers.
And then one challenge
with the attention.
LSTMs can count.
In fact, they can count.
They can learn interesting
temporal patterns.
But attention is
permutation invariant.
So we had to actually
add position.
We had to add position
information so
that we could learn ordering.
So we add position
information at the input,
which gets transmitted
to the other layers
through the residual
connections.
And the original paper--
we had post-LayerNorm.
But later on, we realized
that, as we actually
make the model deeper,
post-LayerNorm doesn't
allow you to train effectively.
So we had to--
then we used a
pre-LayerNorm formulation,
which was also observed in
the original ResNet papers.
And so the model is
basically-- all right.
You've got your input and
you have spatial mixing.
Spatial mixing to attention,
feed forward layers.
And this repeats.
And the difference
on the decoder side
is that you also now have
encoder-decoder attention
at every layer.
If there's any questions-- yeah?
Yes.
What was your intuition
behind the [INAUDIBLE]??
Post-LayerNorm?
Oh.
So it ended up-- so if you
do post-LayerNorm, then--
actually, let's-- do
I have that slide?
Let me check.
Probably I've deleted it.
But if you do
post-LayerNorm, then you
are basically squashing both the
residual and the additive parts.
So when you-- so your
activations from the lower
layers keep getting-- keep
going through the LayerNorms.
But in pre-LayerNorm,
you're only--
only your residual path
has a LayerNorm, which
means your activations all the
way from the bottom of the model
are free.
They're untouched, and
they can pass through.
Yeah.
So until this point,
we haven't discussed
why did we-- we
haven't discussed
multi-head attention, which
ended up being very important.
So one of the problems
with attention is that--
imagine if you wanted to--
so oftentimes, language
is about understanding
who did what to whom.
So in this case, the cat
licked the owner's hands.
So who licked what?
The cat licked the owner.
So now, if you actually
want to combine information
from these two slots, these
positions, these vectors,
then the best you
could do with attention
is 0.5, 0.5 with the single
layer at half probability,
half probability.
But then they get
mushed together.
But now imagine the strength
that a convolution has.
It can actually have a--
That actually should have--
oh, OK.
Well, I think the point
will still come across.
So now what a convolution
can do is-- because it has--
it basically applies--
essentially, a convolution--
in this case, it's a 5 by 1.
And all it really
does is it just
applies a different linear
transformation at each position.
So it can take any--
and because these linear
transformations are different,
it can-- the first linear
transformation can learn.
I'm going to take a little
bit of information from here.
And I'm going to
put them together.
And the attention-- the best
way that you could actually
just do this is best
by averaging out
[INAUDIBLE] these things.
But having different
linear transformations
allows you to take a part
of the embedding here,
a part of the embedding here,
mix it up, and then maybe put it
together without actually then
interfering with each other.
And multi-head attention,
which is a bit like--
basically, a
multi-tape-- multi-head
of a multi-head Turing machine
with different read-write heads.
Essentially, it allows-- you
start getting you that property
back, where now what you
do is you essentially--
you now-- you bring
back the ability
to select different
parts of the input.
So you chop up the
hidden dimension
into independent pieces.
And then each one of them
is now able to do attention.
So now you can have probability
1 in this place and probability
1 in this other sub space,
instead of having 0.5, 0.5.
So now you don't have to
get these averaging effects.
You can actually be selective.
And also, for
computational reasons, we--
instead of actually having
eight attention layers of--
or six attention heads
of d dimensions, we had--
or eight attention
heads of d dimensions,
we had eight attention
heads of d by 8 dimensions.
So we wouldn't incur any more--
we wouldn't incur any
more any more FLOPs
for the same amount of FLOPs.
But that's only half the story
because the attention heads
themselves turn out
to be quite expensive,
which then later on
had to be-- there
were improvements that
needed to be made.
And the most important part--
probably the most important
result was that,
with the transformer,
we were able to outperform
previous ensemble
models as well.
And that was very, very
exciting that, hey,
the single model actually
is able to outperform
previous ensemble models.
And not only that.
And this is a machine
translation WMT 2014
English-German and
English-French machine
translation tasks.
And not only were we able
to do it in less FLOPs,
but also, these--
it was very clear that this
was a very general model.
We immediately
applied it to parsing,
and we were able to get, with a
small model, excellent results.
So in some sense, we were--
this was very exciting because
this meant that, all right, now
this consolidation that we're
trying to go for in machine
learning-- we probably
have a model that's
more general than
what we had before.
And we can now throw
it at different--
maybe we can now throw
it at different problems.
And ultimately, why?
Because it would be helpful
to have a single model
that's able to combine
representations from speech,
images, and language.
And if you had a general
substrate that worked well
in all tasks, then
potentially we
could get to the single
multimodal model.
Sometimes, interpretability
is like tea leaves.
It's like reading tea leaves.
So one should be careful.
But it was nice that
the attention by itself
can give you some
interpretability.
And we were able to see how
some of these attention heads
or some of these
attention mechanisms
were actually able to learn
long-distance relationships.
Some actually learned to be--
early on in the transformer,
we saw this generally invariant
pattern, where some
of the attention heads
basically turned out to
just look like convolutions.
They were just they were just
pulling in local information.
There's, of course, now
being much more advanced work
with some of the
mechanistic interpretability
stuff with grokking
and the stuff that
is happening at Anthropic,
which is where they're learning.
Now they're actually learning
how to interpret these induction
heads.
So it's interesting.
But we were able to see
some anecdotal evidence
of these heads actually
performing very, very distinct
and clear actions.
So if there's any
more questions, then--
no more?
I'll pause for a second.
Yeah?
Do you buy the research from--
that it's the
induction heads that
are causing the in-context
learning [INAUDIBLE]??
Yeah.
It's hard to tell because--
so from what-- I haven't
looked at the most recent work.
But they've solved this
issue of superposition.
Is that right?
So now, with having solved that,
they're able to roughly-- does
that roughly mean
that now they're
able-- they'll be able to
assign distinguishing features
to each one of these sets
and be able to explain it?
From what I understand-- or the
in-context learning part is--
is that-- is it that
they have to show it?
Or is it that they're saying
that in-context learning happens
because of induction heads?
Yeah.
The latter.
Oh, it's the latter.
Yeah.
It's not clear because--
yeah.
I think there's probably
many, many kinds of--
in-context learning is shown to
work in so many different tasks
that--
and actually, I haven't
followed this quite well.
I don't know if--
I don't know specifically--
What do the induction
heads typically do?
What kinds of
properties do they have?
Do you know what kinds of
mechanisms do they have?
OK.
So yeah.
So since both of us
don't know this really,
really well, I won't be
able to go very far here.
But I'm not sure
if they've gotten
to the point where
they're able to explain
most of in-context learning
because of induction heads.
From what I understand,
they might have.
Yeah.
Does anybody know about
the induction heads?
OK.
Over the years-- so
there have been a few--
there have been many papers.
But there have
been a few changes
that have been important.
There have been a few
changes that have stuck.
And the new
transformers typically
have these improvements.
And you'll go from bottom
to top with some of them
and see which ones
have actually stuck.
So we started with the first.
One of the biggest problems with
self-attention was that it was--
that self-attention itself
is permutation invariant.
You need to do position
information in order
for it to learn some kind
of temporal structure.
And in the original transformer,
we used these sinusoids.
And we had hoped that it would
actually learn relative position
encodings because you could
decompose the position
encoding of another--
you could decompose the position
embedding of another position
as some linear function of
the previous one, and some--
and another factor,
which is-- which
depends on the relative
distance between the two.
But that didn't happen.
Learned position encodings in
the original paper did as well.
And so we were not
quite able to get the--
we were not quite able to get
these model relative distances
using the sinusoids.
So then a couple of
important-- and this
is a very biased sample.
But I think it generally covers
a large category of these--
it covers a large set of papers.
There's roughly
three categories.
And all of them are now
explicitly learning--
explicitly for learning
relative embeddings.
So in the relative
position transformer,
we had an embedding for every
pair of relative positions.
And using that, we
basically then--
we did a Dot-Product
of that embedding
with the query that
produced a logit that
was-- that modulated according
to the relative distance.
And we found this
to be extremely--
we found this to be extremely
useful for translation.
And I'll show it also in music.
Another-- maybe a
simplification--
this is the Alibi paper,
where this is non-parametric.
These are not learned,
where, instead
of an embedding for
every pair of positions,
you actually have a single bias.
So you basically just add
a single bias to the logit.
And you can either
learn it, or you can use
a heuristic, which Alibi did.
And one other advantage about
relative position encodings
is that they could
potentially allow
you to extrapolate to new-- to
longer sequence lengths, which
you couldn't do with
absolute position encodings.
I'm curious about the room--
about what the room thinks here.
But I believe that the latest
incarnation of relative position
encodings, where this is--
I believe it's called the row
former, where they basically
just rotate the embedding
with every pair of dimensions
a little bit.
And the angle of
rotation depends
on your actual
absolute distance.
But what ends up happening
is, when you do the attention
operation, you end up
getting relative-- you end up
basically getting
an effect where
you're modulating the logit
based on relative distance.
So now what's remarkable
about this approach, what's--
it combines the
best of both worlds.
It's absolute
position encodings.
Relative position
encodings had a couple
of challenges in that you had
to maintain an extra logit for--
or an embedding for every pair.
So there was a lot of them.
So it ended up
increasing your memory.
Here-- these are actually
absolute position encodings.
But they give
you-- they ended up
giving you the relative
modulation in the attention
operation that you needed.
And I believe the consensus is
that this is the most successful
position encoding.
Is that correct?
Or are there-- is there--
are there others that people--
is that the consensus?
OK.
So it looks like-- so I
would say that these relative
rotations are from--
the approach that's in
the reformer is likely--
is basically an actual
new, genuine improvement
that is now going to stay
with the transformer.
And it has all the
great properties
of what you would want.
It's an absolute
position encoding
that gives you
relative effects, which
is what we originally wanted.
And one-- and to emphasize
that we needed relative--
emphasize two things, one, that
modeling interesting temporal
relationships, which is-- which
are really important in music,
requires a good
position representation.
We actually found
significant improvements
in the music transformer.
Is it possible to play this?
OK.
So here is a--
all right.
Here's a priming sequence.
This is work by--
work by Anna Huang, by the way.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
This is in-context
learning in music
because you actually
see this prompt.
And you ask the
model to complete it.
So now this is the
vanilla transformer.
And you can already--
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So you can see that
these were using--
we tried both learned
and sinusoids.
And you can see that it
starts all peppy and happy,
but then just languishes
into something
really sad and confused.
So it's not able
to capture these
because music has these
interesting motifs, where--
well, there's motifs
at different levels
because there's some
repetition locally.
But there's a repetition across
the entire piece as well.
So now here this is with
the relative transformer.
And this is with the
first approach, where
we had relative embeddings.
And we had to develop a
compute-efficient approach
to actually--
by using some matrix
calisthenics to actually put
the logits in the right place.
So you can read the paper.
It's fun.
So here is same prime sequence.
And let's see the completion.
Here.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So Anna, who's the first
author of this paper, and also
a musician, tells me that
this actually captures
a lot of structure in music.
It sounds nicer than
the previous one.
But maybe it depends on
what people's tastes are.
Maybe some avant
garde jazz fan would
like the second-- would
like the first piece.
But the point here is
that the difference
is pretty clear between
not working and working.
And I think people-- it'd
be fun to try this out
with the new rotary
position encodings.
All right.
So walking up-- now that we have
a-- we have a good mechanism--
a better mechanism
than we originally
had for modeling
relative distances.
And there's advancements on top
of the rotary position encodings
where, by adjusting the
base frequencies, you can--
when you encounter
longer sequences,
you can just adjust
the base frequencies.
And then the model
is not going to--
the model is not
going to degrade.
So that has good properties.
Probably the--
there's been-- there
have been several
important contributions
to the attention
piece itself, which
is the primary workhorse here.
It's the one that-- you can
think of it as-- it's either--
there's induction heads that
are learning how to copy.
Or maybe all it's really doing
is just routing information
so that the giant feed
forward layers can actually
learn the important features.
But there's broadly two
classes of problems.
There are two classes of issues
with the attention mechanism.
One that was brought up
today that's very evident
is long context itself.
So the complexity,
as we remember,
was quadratic in the
length of the sequence.
And once your sequences
get very, very long--
once your sequences get very,
very long, then it not only--
There's one problem.
It's going to become very-- it's
going to become computationally
expensive.
But it's also the logits that
are going to become infeasible.
So there's generally a
few groups of papers.
One is restricting
attention windows.
And we did this for images where
we had local 1D and 2D attention
for images.
In the first one, we actually
just rasterized the image.
And we had local 1D attention,
which is very similar
to the sliding window
attention in the recent--
in the [INAUDIBLE] paper.
And then in the--
in the 2D case, we have
a spatial 2D attention.
Then there were these
sparse versions,
where you actually-- you
had these specific patterns
over many layers.
You could think about it as--
if you have these sparse
matrices, how many of them
do you have to multiply
with each other
until you get a
really dense matrix?
So roughly this turns
out to be-- so here,
you can get connectivity.
Is that for me?
OK.
You can get connectivity
between distant pixels,
or distant notes in a musical
tune, or words pretty quickly.
And then there's the
second one, which
is-- which there hasn't
been enough work.
And there's some
challenges there.
But it's these unstructured
sparse attention approaches.
And they're typically-- they're
essentially-- what they're--
at a higher level, what they're
really trying to do is--
Imagine that I walked up to
you, and I told you that-- hey,
these are the bunches
of tokens that just
have very high intersimilarity.
They're likely to
attend to each other.
How quickly can I approximate
it without actually having
to do the whole computation?
Two approaches.
In routing attention, you
use vector quantization.
And in the LSH or the--
I forget what it's called.
I think I forgot the
name of the paper.
But they used-- but in
this paper, they used LSH.
And in the routing transformer,
most layers were actually local.
The final layers,
which typically
are the ones that like
to end up-- that end up
doing modeling--
that end up modeling
these long-distance
relationships,
were the ones that actually used
this content-based, unstructured
sparse attention.
And the results were-- the
results were generally better.
And it's also interesting
that maybe you
can build-- we can build models
with-- on very long sequences,
where most layers
are fairly local.
And you have only a few
layers that are actually doing
these long-distance attentions.
Now, one of the bigger
challenges there-- actually,
even though it ended up being--
even though you end up--
you end up nullifying
a lot of the FLOPs
that you would do if
you did full attention.
The problem always ends
up being memory movement.
Always ends up being
memory movement.
And there's still-- there's
still more innovation
to be done here.
Also, with memory
bandwidth improving,
maybe some of these approaches
become more feasible today
than they were
late-- than we did--
when we wrote these papers.
But this is an
interesting approach,
where you're essentially
trying to approximate
the original attention matrix.
Sorry.
This is a silly thing.
But clarification-- how
is this [INAUDIBLE] scheme
very different from just
convolutions that are sparse?
In the sense that
you're losing a lot
of the long-distance
or unrelated contexts
from any arbitrary
pairs of elements.
So how do you--
So I would say that this is
similar to the convolution
there.
If you did this perfectly,
then what you didn't attend to
would very likely have a
very low attention weight.
You're essentially trying to
guess, as best as you can,
what would have
attended to each other.
And so it uses its content
based on structure sparsity.
And there's probably
more interesting work
to be done there.
Maybe, instead of actually
just doing it a token
at a time, where you end up
doing a lot of memory movement,
you end up deciding which chunks
want to self-attend to which
chunks.
So then you just move
entire chunks at a time.
So there's-- I think there's
some interesting directions
here.
And of course--
And frankly, the ones
that ended up sticking
are the simplest
ones that are also--
that are-- because
structured sparsity is easy.
You're able to optimize it
easily on modern accelerators.
So again, physics-- you should
make physics your friend.
Yeah.
And so, typically,
local attention,
or sliding into attention--
we're still seeing it
often appear and do well.
These other very--
really wild and--
but very expressive,
unstructured, sparse attention
approaches typically
haven't quite succeeded.
There's, of course,
linear attention variants
that I don't think today are
in any of the state of the art
architectures.
There were other approaches
that-- hey, instead of actually
doing n squared,
you do n squared
d, where you do
n-- you have some--
you learn new k embeddings,
where you do NKD,
and then you do NDK.
So you basically factor
it just like an analog
of matrix factorization.
Something that's one
other approach that's
interesting, that I would like
myself to actually investigate,
is--
we are seeing, in general,
using retrieval as a tool.
So why don't you just pretend
that your memories themselves
were documents and use
retrieval as a tool there?
So the memorizing
transformer basically--
it essentially does
a mix of local.
And it then retrieves from
very, very long memories.
And they find that you
don't need to train
the model from scratch.
All you need to do is
adapt with this approach
on some small amount
of data, and you're
able to learn a good
retrieval mechanism.
I think it's quite interesting.
It still comes in this
content-based decision
of what I should attend to.
But I like the fact that
it just makes retrieval
a tool that you can use
either on your own memories.
Or you could use
it on documents.
It's a nice generalizing.
It's a nice general view
of looking at things.
So now the second piece,
which you basically--
you run into not all--
you run into the issue that
not all FLOPs are equal.
So if you look at the-- if you
look at the memory hierarchy,
a lot of your activations in--
that are stored in the GPU
HBM, which today, in the H100s,
is about 80 gigabytes-- but
the H100 is 80 gigabytes.
And the A100s used
to be 40 gigabytes.
So there's limited amount
of high-bandwidth memory.
And so you have to first go
from high-bandwidth memory
to the SRAM.
And then you have to go to the
compute elements, and then back.
So every single
time-- and this is--
it probably-- and whenever--
If interested, you can
look at roofline analysis.
The roofline analysis actually
gives you a nice picture
to characterize for any device
where you would need-- where
your workload or
operation needs to be so
that you can actually
effectively utilize
the compute as much.
You want to be compute-bound
because, ultimately,
if you don't calculate
representations--
if you don't calculate, you're
not going to get any output.
But if you spend a lot of
time moving things around
and spend less relative
time calculating,
then you're actually--
you're wasting effort.
So one of the-- so [INAUDIBLE]
standard attention mechanism.
One of the issues is that--
so imagine you have
your queries, keys,
and values all in your memory.
So then you need to then--
your standard approach would
be, you move it to-- you
move it from HBM.
You do the calculations.
You compute the attention.
You compute the logits.
You move logits back into HBM.
And then you compute softmax--
the softmax back into HBM.
And then you basically load the
probabilities and the values
then to then finally
compute the outputs.
So the arithmetic
intensity, or--
the arithmetic intensity
or operational intensity,
which is the amount
of FLOPs that you
do per byte on attention--
even though it's
less FLOPs than, say,
a 1 by 1 convolution,
it had more-- it is lower
because it typically
has more memory movement,
whereas 1 by 1 convolutions
have less memory movement.
You just move the weights.
You move the activations.
You do the calculations.
Then you bring them back.
And same goes for
convolutions, too.
And convolutions have a very
high arithmetic intensity.
So it's not that you just want
the highest arithmetic intensity
or operational
intensity operations
because you still want to
have useful parameters.
So it's a trade-off.
So a lot of-- so there's a bunch
of improvements that will stick.
It's almost-- they're
almost certain--
likely to stay that try
to combat this issue,
both at training time, because
your logits can get really big,
but also at inference
time, when your KD--
when you're doing attention and
when you're doing inference,
then you have a single query,
but your KD cache, right?
You have to maintain
your keys and values.
That can grow quite a bit, so
you have to move that around.
And so the first step is simple.
Let's just decrease
the activation memory.
So the multi-query approach,
where it's basically
a multiple-- so you reduce--
you have multiple queries,
but you reduce the number
of read heads to just one.
So you have just one
key and one value.
That does reduce
your expressivity.
So grouped-query-- which is now
a simple balance that basically
says, hey, let's
not take the extreme
of having all this
temporary activation memory.
Let's actually group
it so different
queries-- so a bunch of queries
will attend to the same keys
and values.
And then what ends
up happening is--
another point to note
here is that all of this
is relative because most of
the work in these very, very--
Oh, by the way, third
approach, actually,
that I should say
of not worrying
about your attention is just
to make your model really big.
Because then you just care about
your feed forward computations.
And your attention computations
are just a small slice of that,
so you don't worry about it.
So typically, in
these larger models--
even though grouped query
attention has more activation
memory than multi-query
with these large models,
it's still a much larger--
it's not a much larger--
it's still a smaller proportion
of what you're doing in the feed
forward.
So you're certifying.
So, I guess, three things.
Ignore.
Make it really big.
Second is, I guess, you--
by even the-- with
prolonged context,
you can do some of the--
some of these approaches
that we talked about.
But then you also have
these system optimizations,
which are pretty cool.
So the softmax has an
interesting property that you
can compute in online fashion.
You can compute
it incrementally.
If you've got a
bunch of logits-- so
you're streaming them.
If you've got a partial softmax
and a new logit comes in,
you can update it.
You can update it in
an online fashion.
So what does that mean?
That means that now you
never need it to write
logits or the P's into the HBM.
So you save a lot.
If there's an extremely
long sequence,
you end up writing a lot.
So you save on that.
And both these approaches
end up-- in one case,
the first paper was on TPUs
that introduced this property,
or took advantage of this
property, [INAUDIBLE]
the property to
be able to compute
the softmax in an
online fashion,
and the second paper, which
is now flash attention today.
They've had many advancements.
They actually had some systems
level optimization, where they--
now you can actually have very,
very long sequences on GPUs--
the optimizations of GPUs
by basically not moving
the logits back into
HBM using this online--
using this property, and
also writing the right forms
that use [INAUDIBLE] and
everything, use the GPU.
Any questions?
OK.
What's the time?
So we are basically--
20 minutes.
So I'll finish in time.
So I just covered these two.
There's many, many.
I guess there's other
important improvements.
So we talked about the pre and
post versus post-LayerNorm.
There's been some changes of the
feed forward layers themselves.
You can stare at the
feed forward layers.
If you stare at
anything long enough,
everything becomes attention.
But it's true in the
feed forward case
that, if you look at it, you
can think about them as--
it looks like attention.
And there was a paper that
turned that into a bit--
turned that-- turned
those into memories.
It was originally by Facebook.
I actually forget what it was.
But it didn't--
And the feed forward
layers just stayed.
We typically haven't seen a
lot of improvements on them.
There have been some--
there have been some efforts
on higher order attention right
now.
Attention, if you
think about it,
is a third-order interaction.
You have queries,
keys, and values, but--
right now.
But you could imagine actually
having four-order interactions,
where you're actually computing
logits of pairs of things
against all pairs of things.
So these are now higher order
interactions, where now you
can have complicated geometries
that you actually include
in your attention computation.
And maybe it's important
for, say, biology, or--
biology, but it's not
been explored much.
What has actually worked
and is likely to now stay
is some approaches
on faster decoding.
Not quite the original less or
non-autoregressive aspirations
that we had, but these
more speculative decoding,
where the heuristic
there is pretty simple.
Yeah.
If you want, instead of
generating from a heavy model,
generate from a
really light model
that captures the diversity.
And score with a heavy model.
So then you re-rank the list.
And that ends up
working quite well.
And most state of the art--
most production deployments
likely use speculative decoding.
So now switching gears.
I guess we started this--
we started by quoting the
Dartmouth Conference, where
they wanted to build
a single machine.
And the question now is with
large language models that
are now eating up
most of the internet,
are we getting-- are
we quite getting there?
And we are seeing
some remarkable--
we're finally seeing
self-supervised learning work
at a scale that--
work at an unprecedented
scale, where, now,
by digesting carefully curated
and colossal amounts of text
with very, very large
models, you're able to then--
they're able to
perform, presumably,
or still waiting to be
confirmed, tasks that are--
or they're able to actually
perform at least a large--
a broad variety of tasks by just
specifying them in the prompt.
And it's now-- it's almost like
now, you have a new computer.
And for people here who are
really excited about the future
of agents, now they can
program thousands of agents
with the same computer.
Or maybe you-- now
they have agents
that they can-- several
agents that they can program
with the same computer
then that then
coordinate to solve problems.
So we're getting-- we're much
closer to the single model not
quite being able to specify
all the rules of intelligence,
but at least learning
all the rules from data.
We're very close.
We're much closer
than we were before.
Now, this doesn't include
all the important--
all the important
specialization that
has to happen after the
chip or the alignment
that you have to do to make
the model more steerable.
And as it stands
today, the scaling laws
that the transformer
exhibits are better
than any other existing model.
So there's an interesting
question of which--
can we build a better model?
And there are efforts, I
guess, from the Stanford--
from Chris Ray's lab, there
have been a couple of efforts.
There's been some
revival of [INAUDIBLE],,
but I think the only thing I'll
say there is that the attention
operation itself--
this operation of actually
moving information
around or routing information
based on content--
it's very, very useful.
And it's maybe not
a surprise that
this general spatial mixing,
upsampling, downsampling,
architecture has kind of
stayed with computer vision
and language, now
with the transformer.
So there are some invariants
that are likely to stay,
but I do think
that maybe there--
and there is certainly much
more room there to improve--
I mean not just in the
architecture but on data itself.
Like, there's probably two
X improvements on data.
But I wouldn't say
that there aren't
architectures in the future that
will get better scaling laws.
They might, but
there are properties
about the transformers,
such as self-attention
and its general
structure that is
likely we're going to see in
future architectures to come.
Also it's hard to really
think of a modern--
like, if somebody
really, really wanted
to study large scale
modern transformers,
you'd have to
study all reduces--
infiniband, rocky, and-- like,
whether you get congestion
and you have very, very
large clusters, so it's--
So the computer is no--
the transformer is
now in some sense
a data center because
it's now split up.
These large transformers,
potentially tens of thousands
of GPUs, and so
now, you actually
have to really focus on several
parts-- the infrastructure
[INAUDIBLE] and
the model itself.
But what's really
interesting I think is--
I was just thinking of the
smallest model that has
exhibited emergent phenomena.
Well, so we certainly know
that GPT-4, which is likely--
I don't know if you're
allowed to say it--
like, trillion parameters.
Yes.
That's a trillion
parameter size model.
That's what everybody says--
size model.
And then you have
grokking, which
is a two-layer transformer that
has this weird emergent behavior
that when you just keep
training it on just
on some amount of data, suddenly
it just exhibits a space shift.
So we're lucky.
There are these really--
there's weirdness everywhere.
There's weirdness in small
models and large models,
and maybe we can learn
something about large models
by studying these small
models one would hope.
But it's funny.
Like, there's still
unexplained phenomena
in very, very large models
and very, very small models.
But large transformers are
no more just like a colab.
I mean, it could still
be, but it's you have to
there's so many--
there's so much that you
have to keep in your stack
in order to really
optimize this model.
Of course, some of the
very exciting directions
are LLMs using tools.
So now, the benefits of-- now,
language models or transformers
are actually starting to
use external entities,
so they're connecting with
the rest of the world,
and I guess that's a good pitch
for-- it makes a lot of sense
to actually build products
today because it's through
interactions with--
Like, if you want to get to the
next tranche of capabilities,
where will they come from?
And likely, with a
lot of usage, you
will learn much more about
how to guide these models
and how to train them
without them in vacuum.
Now, you can definitely
do very, very important
work still with a
smaller model, or even
without building a
product-- without building
a product because there's
so many important unsolved
problems.
And maybe you shouldn't
even work on the transformer
because it's like
burning man right now.
Everybody's going
to the same party,
but I think that you
will be able to build
new capabilities once this
human machine collaboration.
Of course, you know,
teaching models or models
being able to express
what they don't know--
How do you learn new
skills at inference time
important for this
interesting work?
I think on Minecraft that
showed some evidence of this.
It's also important for agents.
And a great property that
some of these diffusion models
have is the more compute you
spend, the potentially better
the quality of the image gets,
but we don't exactly quite
have that for language.
And what does that mean?
So today, the models
that can reason
that are the most proficient
reasoning and planning
are also the largest ones.
Can we separate it out?
Can just smaller models that
do some adaptive thinking
and are able to match the
capabilities of potentially
larger models and
reasoning and planning?
And maybe the answer
is going to come
by connecting to external
planners and planners,
or maybe with better
representations of data
you can actually
reason better on it.
Also this is again a
more systems piece,
but it's fascinating how low you
can actually get on your on--
how low you can--
how few bits you can actually
use and still get something
useful out.
We already went from--
the original transformer was
trained on 32-bit precision.
Then we went to
bfloat16, and now there's
good signs that INT8
and fp8 would also work.
And I think there's useful work
to be done that again going back
to the same--
this argument about
if you're actually--
If you're using fewer bits
to represent a number,
you're actually transmitting
fewer bits from HPM,
so actually, you can get faster.
And you utilize the-- you can
utilize your matrix multipliers
much more effectively.
That was it.
Many topics but hopefully
covered something fun.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Can you talk about what
you're working on now?
Yeah.
So I'm a co-founder of a startup
with my tranformer co-author,
Nikki, and we're working on
building models that will
ultimately automate workflows.
And we're starting
with data, so it's
very puzzling what
happens in a company.
Companies are basically just
masses of dark knowledge, right?
And there's very
few people that have
both the technical privilege
and the understanding to ask
questions-- like,
typically analysts.
But unless you understand
the less effective
your company can be, so
how can you eventually
help anyone become an effective
analyst in some sense, right?
So help them ask
the right question,
help them figure out eventually
the why's, which then requires
some kind of
counterfactual reasoning
that's fairly complicated.
But start with data
since it's so important,
and companies are
essentially drowning in it.
And then it can be
spread out from there,
and then try to automate other
workflows and then enterprise.
But we believe that some
of the early signs that
we're [INAUDIBLE] and what--
and our position is that--
I believe that this is going to
require a full stack approach
to not just them building the
model because you can then
control what feedback you get.
And so if you have a gap in
the model, you ask for that.
You start to get that
feedback, so then you
can improve the model.
So that's what we're doing.
Yeah, it's-- please talk to us.
Yeah.
I'm surprised to
hear that you're
fairly bullish about
schools in the end.
Like, [INAUDIBLE]
third party things.
We talked about in the beginning
that your motivation was
transformers enabled us
to get rid of pipelines,
but I feel like [INAUDIBLE]
again, so I'm surprised.
Can you talk about that?
And where do you
think [INAUDIBLE]??
Right.
So I mean, so until we get to
the point where it's like--
we're turtles all the way down--
transformers all the way down.
I think that tool
just allows you to--
so it's kind of like how do you
interface with a machine that
can really like--
that can think right?
Yeah.
You have to build some
kind of interface,
and if you build a
useful functionality,
you want the machine to be
able to take your functionality
in the end and do general
useful things with it, right?
And I think that
using tools is just
a way of leveraging things
that people have built
and software out there.
Certain tools will probably get
absorbed in the model, right?
Some others won't, and that
still gives us the ability to--
it still gives us
the ability to--
and certain things that
transformers shouldn't even do.
Sorry.
I mean, like, you
don't want to spend
a billion flops per position
to calculate two numbers.
You don't want to
spend more flops
to do an operation that requires
like 1 billion flops, right?
So there are certain things
that the model should not do.
It should use external-- it
should use external tools.
And there are
certain things that--
certain kind of thinking
that the model should do.
So even from a
capability perspective,
there's an important question of
what all capabilities should be
in this neural network, right?
But then also being
able to utilize
the work that other others
have done-- software
that other people
have built. Yeah.
Can you talk more about
why the original approach
of decoding parallely and
then [INAUDIBLE] refining it.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] why that
didn't work and what.
Yeah.
So sometimes if you know exactly
why things work maybe you can
make them work, but
it ended up being--
so we were able to do silly
things, like randomly sort,
which means that if somebody
walks up to you with
a sequence--
you can-- I mean, you
can break two modes.
Like, you can say
ascending or descending.
So how do I say this?
So typically, when you decode--
imagine that when
you give a prompt,
you have many
possible completions.
And each time you make a
choice, you narrow that space.
And each time-- another
So and you have a very--
and you have learned
to narrow the set
of all possible in some
sense paths in a way
the model doesn't have to decide
what's the order in which you
have to do it, right?
When you're kind
of-- when you're
doing this less or
non-autoregressive generation,
you have to do both, right?
And learning both
simultaneously is hard.
I mean, but eventually, I think
that if for a particular--
I think this is
probably true, right?
If an oracle walked
up to me and said
this is the order in which
all these sentences should
be generated, first you should
generate these three words,
then you should generate these
other two, then these other two.
If somebody walked up to
me and gave me this oracle
ordering for all
of human language,
I think you would have
a much better chance,
and you could actually get
this less non-autoregressive
generation at least working.
So what are the two
things you said?
So one thing was basically
the ordering itself,
and I think it kind of has to do
that because the ordering helps
you then lock down the modes.
It narrows down what you're
going to generate next.
So ultimately, I
think it does boil
down to what's the right
non-autoregressive ordering,
and that could be either
you're still generating
one word at a time but
not autoregressively,
or you're generating a
few and then based on
that you're generating
the other few.
So the words that you
can generate all at once
should be conditionally
independent of each other.
What you've generated so far
should have completely explained
them, and then what you
generate after should again be--
they should be
conditionally independent.
So how do you learn these
conditional independencies?
Yeah.
If somebody walked up to
me and gave them to me,
I think they probably
learned them.
Yeah.
It's more of a [INAUDIBLE].
Recently, [INAUDIBLE].
And I think more of the thinking
is that only an extremely small
spot doesn't help
them to actually learn
what the real world actually
works and [INAUDIBLE] we
had a good idea of that truth
and the real world in general.
Do you agree with him?
Do you think that [INAUDIBLE]?
So yeah, I think it's
interesting [INAUDIBLE] you
can learn a world model
with just language, right?
So I mean, some of these
models are not exactly
being learned that way.
You're doing [INAUDIBLE].
You're getting some
feedback, so which
means there's some
you're applying some--
they are modifying themselves
to some preference,
so it's not just a
pure language model.
But it's interesting.
So you've seen some of the
work, where robotics is now
potentially starting to
flourish because they're
able to use these large
models as planners, right?
And so I think that
it's surprising how
much of the world-- how much
information about the world
that they carry.
If I understand, is it
right that the [INAUDIBLE]
can work basically use a
language model now as a planner?
Yes.
Right?
And then they left
the rest of it
to just the standard perception
and the classical tasks
[INAUDIBLE] robotics.
So I mean, that's--
now, while John is
probably still right,
but the usefulness of it is
evident in something that
needs world knowledge, right?
So I think you can do a
lot with what you have.
I mean, probably-- yeah.
I mean, we still haven't quite
extracted all the usefulness
out of these models as
well, and it might be right,
but there's still a
lot more to be gained.
Yeah.
So similar to the previous
question, and you've
also been talking about
emergent abilities, right?
I'm just curious
to know what are
your thoughts are more on
generalizability and emergent,
especially in the--
I know there was a paper from
Deepmind about the assignment,
yeah.
Yeah.
They can't really generalize
outside of like what they've
been trained on, especially
because these large models
now that they're just
trained on everything.
Is there truly anything left
that's out of distribution
that really sort
of benchmark it on?
So I have been caught
saying that if I
had all my test data
and my training,
I'd make a billion dollars.
Yeah.
So I don't have a problem
with it, but I still think--
OK.
Correct me if I'm wrong,
but the general argument
is that these
models have learned
such a vast set of
distributions and phenomena
that typically when
you interrogate them,
they're often very know very
cleverly blending or bringing
information from what
they've learned, right?
It might-- yes.
And then they have
these algorithmic tasks,
where the models fail
to generalize, right?
So I'll focus on the former.
I think that that's an
incredibly useful property.
It might be that--
So I think the--
maybe the failing is that
we actually don't quite
understand how much we could--
how much is even represented
in text, and second how much--
how far we could go if you're
able to blend information
from different--
like, certainly being able
to write about the Stanford--
this lecture in the rhyme
meter and words of chaucer
is not possible because
nobody did it, right?
But I think that
you could do it.
Now, is that
blending information
from what you already have?
If so that's a--
that means you can-- that's
an incredible skill, right?
I haven't read it.
It's very recent, but
I believe the work.
I think you can show that
these models can generalize,
but I think there's a surprising
amount of seemingly new things
you could do by just
blending information
from what you've already
learned on the internet.
And yeah, largely
probably has to do
that there's so much happening.
Yeah.
So the other question-- yeah.
Yeah, I had a [INAUDIBLE].
I think had an ordering in
mind, and then I came back.
Sorry, but give me a
second [INAUDIBLE]..
I was wondering if you
might have insights
into connecting different
agents, transformers,
or whatnot?
Neuron is a great--
transformer is essentially
like a great connection
of neurons in a specific
way, and it's awesome, right?
So you figured out the best
way to connect them so far.
Agents?
No-- the neurons.
Oh, the neurons.
You're talking about how
to do this in the brain.
No.
The neurons in the
transformer, right?
The transformer is the way
you connect different pieces
together, and then when you
connect everything together,
it works-- transformer.
So I was wondering if
you have some insights
into building systems
that connect and perform
the best together.
Yeah.
And David's not
going to like this.
I like to make this joke-- that
the best agents are actually
using neurons because they can
communicate with each other.
They can update themselves
really, really well,
but what the other
agents are doing.
What is the fundamental
problem by making--
what is the fundamental
issue in making a bunch of--
I'm trying to
understand what are
the fundamental
problems in trying
to make a bunch of
systems work together?
That's what you're asking.
What is goal
decomposition, right?
And one is the second.
Big one is coordination, and
third one is verification.
If you solve a successful
decomposition of the goals
based on what your estimate of
the skills of these agents are,
if you're able to apply
what they've done,
and if you're able
to coordinate,
then I think you could
make a lot of progress.
So while I didn't
answer your question,
I don't know in general
how much progress
we've made in these three
areas, but does somebody
have any input here?
And you have something
that's managing [INAUDIBLE]..
And you want to verify
this [INAUDIBLE]..
So it becomes like a
microprocessor, right?
There's a lot of
training power when
you want to make
sure [INAUDIBLE]
and verify everything,
and break it off.
So you have this display
performance [INAUDIBLE]
everything and making
it efficient over time.
And [INAUDIBLE].
But it's still very early.
No one knows really.
Yeah, right, but--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
These are probably maybe to
some degree necessary as well.
I mean, you--
This is [INAUDIBLE].
It still remains to be
seen with ensemble models.
Now, we have a lot of
[INAUDIBLE] modality,
but the human brain is very
modular, so this modularity
in an emergent phenomena.
You need some special
tricks to make that happen.
Yeah, and by modularity
here you mean that--
is it modularity
in that they have--
this region has
this responsibility,
or even is the
composition different?
The construction different.
What do you mean by that?
Because one, you
could have both.
You could argue that
the responsibility
is diffused across the model.
Mixtures of experts tries to go
in the opposite direction, which
I--
I should have
probably mentioned.
That's another really
exciting direction,
which certainly has
happened to the people
this is going to stick.
I totally missed it.
That kind of that tries to
get the specialization, right?
So maybe that is some
kind of modularity, right?
Learn modularity.
The rest is-- the rest of
responsibility for performing
the task is likely distributed,
but if now you're going to these
subsystems themselves of
different composition,
then you get back to--
and I know that this is a
goal with the pathways project
at Google, where
you wanted to have
these really modular systems
communicate with each other.
And I think there's--
it's just taken so long
to get gradient descent.
Like gradient descent--
in fact, sometimes I
think that we're just
building architecture
to serve gradient descent.
And like, if you can learn
with gradient descent,
it's very useful.
Maybe it's actually possible to
make these modular systems work.
We have some of it
through experts.
And I'd imagine some of these
problems that we discussed.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
All right.
Circling back to
[INAUDIBLE] ago,
you mentioned that the problem
with imploding all at once was
one of the things that--
decode engineering always
has this assumption
that the outputs are
conditionally independent,
but aren't they in a sense that
if you have a latent space--
if you're given a latent
space as your prior,
then your posterior
outputs should
be conditionally independent
of each other, right?
So great point, and where do
you get the latent space from?
Well, from the encoder or
whatever at the beginning.
Right, but there might
be quite a few ways
to translate something, right?
Yeah.
There's multiple-- so if there's
only one mode, then yeah,
it's probably--
But if there's
multiple ways of--
Well, so there's two things.
How much does the latent space
actually carry, by the way,
is an important thing to ask.
How much does it actually carry?
Because it's not just one latent
vector that you're transmitting
every-- you're doing
attention again and again,
but we took this approach,
where we did precisely this.
We autoregressively
generated tokens
in a new vocabulary using
vector quantization.
So the conditional
dependence was
modeled in a latent space,
where we discretized
using vector quantization.
And then based on
that, we generated
everything conditioning,
and that did work.
But again, so that did
work in translation.
There were some
funky issues there,
where the sequence
of latent vectors
were only effective-- were not
effective if you learn directly
on the original data.
You had to do something
like distillation
because distillation itself
throws away potentially some
of the noise.
So generally, lower entropy
data, we wanted to train on it.
The second piece was
for practical systems,
you have to make the whole
thing really, really fast,
but this is a good
research exercise,
but ultimately, it didn't have
the right practical impact
because speculative decoding
practically with what we
have right now can work well.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Yeah, but you're right.
I think if you can
generate-- if you
can generate a good
sufficient latent state,
then yes, you're right.
We can assume-- that
makes everything
conditionally
independent, and yeah--
and we managed to do that a bit.
Managed to do that, but it
wasn't quite good enough.
Yeah.
I guess this is
the last question.
What is it about?
[INAUDIBLE]
That's too personal.
Yeah.
Very personal, and I
have friends there.
They're all really great.
They're doing incredible things.
I think that we'll be surprised
how much there is to do.
And if-- so personal
motivation, right?
There is an entire new--
there's an entire
new bucket of--
a new tranche of
capabilities that you
will get with human
computer interaction.
So you can make a product.
People use it.
They give you feedback
models, get smarter,
and this closed loop
system can really
bring-- can really advance
models and bring value.
That's one.
Second-- I think it's
helpful to have some.
Deep learning benefited
so much from a diversity
of ideas and people pursuing
important directions,
and I would say the same about--
I would say the same about
building company products as
well or building
companies that are--
building new kinds of products
with these models, right?
So I would say that
we have-- there's
so much surface area that we
could do something incredible.
So that's the second piece.
Third, yeah, maybe that's the
more personal-- that I just
want to do my own thing.
Yeah.